Karen Kuykendall papers, 1923-1982
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Karen Kuykendall papers, 1923-1982
MS 243
Kuykendall, Karen
Contains historical material relating to Adolf Hitler and the Third Reich, with emphasis on the character and personality of Adolf Hitler and the decorative arts and relics of the Third Reich.
7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Some volumes were previously cataloged separately under the following numbers: MS 244 through MS 252, MS 255 through MS 258, MS 260, and MS 261.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series
Series I: Biographical Materials and Articles, 1972-1982
Series II: Interviews and Correspondence, 1971-1978
Series III: Material Relating to Adolf Hitler and the Third Reich, 1923-1975
Series IV: Materials Relating to the Art and Architecture of the Third Reich, 1932-1971
Series V: Miscellaneous Oversize Materials, 1928-1971
Scope and Content Note
Contains historical material relating to Adolf Hitler and the Third Reich, with emphasis on the character and personality of Adolf Hitler and the decorative arts and relics of the Third Reich. Includes chiefly clippings, political cartoons, articles, posters, photographs, and miscellaneous memorabilia, 1923-1971. Also includes correspondence and questionnaires from interviews by Karen Kuykendall with individuals who knew Adolf Hitler, including Arno Breker, Gerhard Engel, Hermann Giesler, Heinrich Heim, Richard Schulze-Kossens, Dr. Werner Naumann, Albert Speer, and Gerdy Troost, 1971-1978.
Breker, Arno, 1900- -- Correspondence; Engel, Gerhard -- Correspondence; Giesler, Hermann, 1898- -- Correspondence; Hasselbach, Hans Karl von -- Correspondence; Heim, Heinrich -- Correspondence; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945 -- Comic books, strips, etc; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945 -- Humor; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945 -- Personality; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945 -- Pictorial works; Naumann, Werner -- Correspondence; Speer, Albert, 1905- -- Correspondence; Toland, John -- Correspondence; Troost, Gerdy -- Correspondence; Schulze-Kossens, R.(Richard), 1914- -- Correspondence; Bird, Kenneth, 1887-1965; Marcus, Edwin, 1885-1961; Szyk, Arthur, 1894-1951; Architecture, Modern -- 20th century -- Germany; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Germany; Decorations of honor -- Germany; Medals -- Germany; Military decorations -- Germany; Military paraphernalia -- Collectors and collecting; Military paraphernalia -- Germany; National socialism and art; National socialism and architecture; National socialism -- Philosophy; Nazis -- Pictorial works; World War, 1939-1945 -- Posters; World War, 1939-1945 -- Humor; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Correspondence; Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Materials and Articles, 1972-1982
  - "Recollections by Karen Kuykendall: Growing up in San Diego, California during the 1930's." 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Various articles on the Third Reich. By Karen Kuykendall. No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Hunting: The Joys and Sorrows of Being a Third Reich Relics Collector." Includes mostly black and white photographs and color slides of military decorations and other Third Reich collectibles. Also includes correspondence from various dealers, museums and collectors. By Karen Kuykendall. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original holograph translations of articles from Das III Reich. By Karen Kuykendall. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Interviews and Correspondence, 1971-1978
  - Interview notes. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Professor Arno Breker. 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: General Gerhard Engel, Professor Herman Giesler, Dr. Werner Naumann. 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Dr. Hans Karl von Hasselbach. 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Heinrich Heim. 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Richard Schulze-Kossens. 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Albert Speer. 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Gerdy Troost. 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: John Toland, author of Adolf Hitler. 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series III: Materials Relating to Adolf Hitler and the Third Reich, 1923-1975
  - "Hitler in American and British cartoons." 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Hitler in British cartoons." 1932-1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Cartoons by Marcus." Clippings of political cartoons by Edwin Marcus from the New York Times. 1938-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles from Life magazine, The New York Times, Look magazine, the Police Gazette and others. No Date (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles from Das Illustrierte Blatt, Signal, Collier's and L'Illustration magazines. 1933-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Articles and clippings from Look magazine, The Illustrated London News, The New York Times Book Review, and various newspapers. 1933-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "The Third Reich in Caricature." Der Simplicus 1:34. 1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Adolf Hitler: a questionnaire with essays" by Karen Kuykendall. One bound volume and one copy with author's handwritten notes. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "The Fuehrer's face." Photographs and clippings of Adolf Hitler. 1923-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles from Readers Digest. 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Articles from Readers Digest, Coronet Magazine, Current History, Pageant Magazine, and Forum magazine. Also includes Flemming, George and Don Tapisco. Terror over Berchtesgaden. Booktab; no. 11. New York, NY. 1936-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Excerpts from various books: Waln, Nora. Reaching for the Stars. [Boston: Little, Brown and Co., 1940?]; Lochner, Louis Paul. What about Germany? [London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1943?]; Taylor, Henry J. Men and Power. [New York: Dodd, Mead, 1946?]. No Date (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Articles from: Current Biography, Harper's, American Historical Review, The Living Age, and Current History. 1936-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Publications of the Terramare Office, Berlin: Bouhler, Philipp. Adolf Hitler: A short sketch of his life. Terramare publications; no 1. Sadila-Montau, Hans Heinz. German Political Profiles. Terramare publications; no 2. Adolf Hitler from Speeches, Terramare publications; no 8-10. Grimm, Freidrich. Versailles in Liquidation. Terramare publications; no 3. Schinnerer, Erich. German Law and Legislation. Terramare publications; no 4. Frercks, Rudolf. German Population Policy. Terramare publications; no 5. Edel, Fritz. German Labour Service. 2nd edition. Terramare publications; no 6. Reher, Werner. Social Welfare in Germany. Terramare publications; no 7. 1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Excerpts from various books: Sinclair, Thornton. "The Nazi Party Rally at Nuremberg." Public Opinion Quarterly (October 1938); Henderson, Sir Neville. Failure of a Mission: Berlin 1937-1939. New York, N.Y.: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1940. No Date (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Hitler: miscellaneous articles." No Date (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clippings from newspapers and magazines. No Date (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Various articles and clippings from Time magazine and others. No Date (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Articles from Playboy magazine, Harper's magazine, The Atlantic Monthly and various other popular magazines. No Date (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Clippings from The Los Angeles Times. September-December 1955 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Clippings from German newspapers. 1933 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Various articles, and clippings from American newspapers and magazines. No Date (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Materials Relating to the Art and Architecture of the Third Reich, 1932-1971
  Original items from box 5, vol. 5-7, Memorabilia of the Third Reich, are located in the vault.
  - Bird, Kenneth. "Posters by Fougasse." Color posters from the 'Careless Talk Costs Lives' series. 1941 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Color Slides: Art history color slides mostly Medieval, Baroque, and 19th-20th century architecture. Third Reich Artifacts. No Date (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "The Fuehrer's Treasures: Decorative Arts of the Third Reich" by Karen Kuykendall. No Date (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Art of the Third Reich." Chiefly clippings, photographs and memorabilia such as postcards and uniform charts. 1932-1945 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia of the Third Reich. Includes some originals and some photocopies of photographs, postcards, stationary, stamps, currency, calling cards, propaganda leaflets and other memorabilia from Nazi Germany. The originals of the photocopied items have been placed in the vault. 1932-1945 (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - "Posters of the Third Reich." No Date (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Doehle, Heinrich. Orders and Decorations of the Third Reich. Berlin: Berliner Buch - und Zeitschriften Verlag. English translation by Dr. Doehle, with addenda compiled by Karen Kuykendall. 1943 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Art in the Third Reich". Magazine of Art. Washington, D.C.: The American Federation of Arts. October 1945 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Articles: "Third Reich Art." "Interview with Albert Speer." Playboy magazine 18: 6 (June 1971): 69-204. "Arno Breker: Sculptor Laureate of the Third Reich." The Sunday Times Magazine (November 7, 1971). No Date (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "German Paintings of World War II." No Date (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Designs for Nazi Daggers." No Date (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Medal Collector. Orders and Medals Society of America. 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Oversize Materials, 1928-1971
  - "The Adventures of Adolf Hitler." Volume I. 1928-1939 (Volume 1)
  - "The Adventures of Adolf Hitler." Volume II. 1940-1942 (Volume 2)
  - "The Adventures of Adolf Hitler." Volume III. 1943 (Volume 3)
  - "The Adventures of Adolf Hitler." Volume IV. 1944-1945 (Volume 4)
  - "Hitler in Soviet Cartoons," with English captions. 1941-1945 (Volume 5)
  - Articles and clippings from The New York Times, Collier's, the Saturday Evening Post and others. 1933-1971 (Volume 6)
  - "Adolf Hitler." Photos from the National Archives and Library of Congress. No Date (Volume 7)
  - "Hitler in Mexican cartoons." Clippings primarily from Hoy magazine (Spanish). 1940-1945 (Volume 8)
  - Artur Szyk, Illustrations by Arthur Szyk. Contains full color political cartoons from various sources including Collier's magazine. Also includes lithographic prints of the 'United Nations Series' of stamp album title pages created beginning in 1945 for Canadian philatelist and entrepreneur Kasimir Bileski. 1941-1948 (Volume 9)
  - "The Third Reich." Clippings from newspapers and magazines. Also includes photographs and posters, from American, British, and German publications, and original posters by Karen Kuykendall. Materials are in German and English. No Date (Volume 10)